<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle to Mr. Dryden.</title>
            <author>Rymer, Thomas, 1641-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05082</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2424B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.2[323]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99886987</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99886987</idno>
            <idno type="VID">181644</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05082)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 181644)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A1:1[326])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle to Mr. Dryden.</title>
                  <author>Rymer, Thomas, 1641-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "Dryden, thy wit has catterwauld too long ..."</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Thomas Rymer.</note>
                  <note>Dated: Exeter, Nov. 5. 1688.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dryden, John, 1631-1700. --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:181644:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <head>An Epiſtle to Mr. Dryden.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>DRYDEN,</hi> thy Wit has catterwauld too long,</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Lero, Lero,</hi> is the only Song.</l>
               <l>What Singing, Dancing, Interludes of late</l>
               <l>Stuff, and ſet off our goodly Farce of State?</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Abbevil</hi> can turn a deep intrigue,</l>
               <l>Till firſt well warm'd with Biſhop <hi>Talgol</hi>'s Jigg.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wem</hi> cannot ſleep, or if a Nap he takes,</l>
               <l>His Dream ſome old <hi>Treſſilian</hi> Ballad breaks.</l>
               <l>But was e'er ſeen the like, in Proſe or Metre,</l>
               <l>To this mad Play, or work of Father <hi>P?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At Court no longer Punchionello takes,</l>
               <l>Each Scene, Part, Cue, miſhapen to the <hi>Mac</hi>'s.</l>
               <l>Sucli Plot, and the Cataſtrophe is ſuch,</l>
               <l>We muſt be either <hi>Iriſh</hi> all, or <hi>Dutch.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our very Judges in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like their old Roof, are <hi>Iriſh</hi> Timber all.</l>
               <l>And (bleſs us!) <hi>Iriſh</hi> Wolves are brought to keep</l>
               <l>The Nation, grown now all ſuch ſilly Sheep;</l>
               <l>Such errant Aſſes, errant Cattle made,</l>
               <l>Or to be yoak'd, or ſaddl'd, fleec'd, or flea'd.</l>
               <l>O Martyrs Son! thy deſtiny is ſhown,</l>
               <l>Such props are for a Scaffold, not a Throne:</l>
               <l>So <hi>Iuno,</hi> in her impotence of rage,</l>
               <l>By Heaven deny'd, did Hell's black Powers engage;</l>
               <l>Yet ſped the Heroe: <hi>Iove</hi> and Fate were ſtrong;</l>
               <l>Religious care! He took his Gods along:</l>
               <l>But heark, O heark, the <hi>Belgick</hi> Lion roars,</l>
               <l>And ſhakes afar the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Britiſh</hi> Shoars:</l>
               <l>One Brandy drinks, one mad with Prophecies:</l>
               <l>Lord! what they tell us of ſome Prince from <hi>Frize;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Arms, and the Man they ſing, no <hi>French</hi> fineſs,</l>
               <l>But hearty Blows, and <hi>Brandenburg</hi> Addreſs.</l>
               <l>Hence Vigor, and our Figure come agen,</l>
               <l>We riſe, and walk, all true erected men.</l>
               <l>The force of thoſe <hi>Circaean</hi> Cups ſubdu'd,</l>
               <l>And the wild Charms our new <hi>Armida</hi> brew'd,</l>
               <l>The Witchcraft he (our true <hi>Rinaldo</hi>) broke,</l>
               <l>And grubs the baſe pretenders to his ſtock.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But oh, what Spirit of Deceit afar,</l>
               <l>Poſſeſs'd our Pulpits, and bewitch'd the Bar?</l>
               <l>What Bane, what Miſchief on poor Mortals ſhed</l>
               <l>By Vermin, from the Laws corruption bred?</l>
               <l>Tho to their <hi>Iriſh</hi> Roof no Cobwebs cleave,</l>
               <l>Below what ſtrife and endleſs toyls they weave:</l>
               <l>Wanting brave Strength to ſtrangle men to death;</l>
               <l>What Frauds they hide! What Venom underneath!</l>
               <l>And when ſome ſhorter courſe to Murder's ſhown,</l>
               <l>Cry, O that (luſcious) Point! they gain'd the Crown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sons of the Pulpit the ſame meaſures keep,</l>
               <l>And of that ſame ſtumm'd Cup have drunk as deep.</l>
               <l>Agog for ſome odd tranſubſtantiate thing,</l>
               <l>Chimera reign, and Metaphyſick King,</l>
               <l>Sublim'd to School Divinity texreams,</l>
               <l>Their Brains would crow with Patriarchal Dreams.</l>
               <l>So high from ſolid honeſt wiſdom blown,</l>
               <l>They'd have ſome <hi>Hippo-Centaur</hi> on the Throne.</l>
               <l>Not Law-ordain'd, but by ſome God appointed,</l>
               <l>Not Lay-elected, but be Prieſt-anointed.</l>
               <l>Away this Goblin Witchcraft, Prieſtcraft-Prince;</l>
               <l>Give us a King, Divine, by Law and Senſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now Bar and Pulpit to Dragoons a ſport,</l>
               <l>Their Cauſe is carried to the laſt Reſort.</l>
               <l>Princes in more compendious method teach,</l>
               <l>Force is their way; let old Apoſtles preach.</l>
               <l>What's ſtabliſh'd Law, where ſtanding Armies come;</l>
               <l>Or who'll talk Goſpel to a Kettle Drum?</l>
               <l>When God would hear, where Giants did oppreſs,</l>
               <l>The ſeveral Nations had their <hi>Hercules.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So were the Horns of grizly violence broke,</l>
               <l>So People freed from triple <hi>Geryon</hi>'s yoke.</l>
               <l>The various Snake in <hi>Lerna</hi> Lough that bred,</l>
               <l>That loll'd and hiſs'd to death, at every head.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nemaean</hi> Lion, <hi>Erymanthian</hi> Boar,</l>
               <l>In Bogs that wallow, and on Hills that roar:</l>
               <l>All by his Godlike Proweſs done away,</l>
               <l>Their lawleſs rule, and that Gigantick ſway.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In vain whilſt this high Virtue Nations ſought,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Naſſau</hi>-Houſe were never yet without.</l>
               <l>Nor is confin'd to <hi>Provinces</hi> their care,</l>
               <l>Their generous <hi>labour</hi> neighboring <hi>Kingdoms</hi> ſhare.</l>
               <l>Here the foul Herd flee from his lifted hand,</l>
               <l>That long had made a <hi>Stable</hi> of the Land.</l>
               <l>The Monſter of the Lough, new <hi>Lerna</hi>-Plague</l>
               <l>(But ſcarce in head) the Bog-begotten <hi>Teague,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The ravenous kind, the Harpyes ſharp for prey,</l>
               <l>With Birds obſcene, and uncouth to the day.</l>
               <l>No Den, no Ditch, no rouſting for'em more,</l>
               <l>Now, now is come our <hi>Hercules</hi> aſhore.</l>
               <l>Vile Fraud diſpell'd, and ſuperſtitious Miſts:</l>
               <l>He from our Temple drives all knaviſh Prieſts.</l>
               <l>Then warmer <hi>Wallop,</hi> in due Scarlet ſhown,</l>
               <l>To Coffee-<hi>Dick</hi> bequeaths his ruſty Gown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh <hi>Dryden,</hi> if this <hi>Hercules</hi> were thine,</l>
               <l>How wou'd his Club, and <hi>Atlas</hi>-ſhoulders ſhine:</l>
               <l>How wou'dſt thou all our Maids of Honor fright,</l>
               <l>With naughty Tale, of <hi>Fifty</hi> in a night?</l>
               <l>Howe'er, no more let <hi>Xavier</hi> mat thy Pen,</l>
               <l>No Miracle to Forty thouſand Men.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When Law, and bald Divinity begins,</l>
               <l>Why then, the marvel that a Poet ſins?</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Exeter,</hi> 
                  <date>Nov. 5. 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
